- To understand how RADIUS
works, what I want to start off
with are these three blocks,
and these three blocks
are gonna represent
three different devices.
Now way over here on the right,
we're gonna have a RADIUS server.
Now a RADIUS server is just
a system that's running
some type of RADIUS
authentication software.
There's Microsoft IAS.
There's third-party tools
like Steel-Belted Radius.
There are open-source
ones like OpenRADIUS.
So it's some type of
authentication software
that's running on a system here.
Now the next thing you're going
to have is a RADIUS client.
Now the RADIUS client is not who's
actually being authenticated.
His job is to handle authentication
requests from RADIUS supplicants.
So these are the guys who
want to get authenticated.
He's just the intermediary that makes
the request to the server itself.
So if we take a look at
this, this is gonna be a
let's say we have a wireless
network for example.
So what I could do here,
let's have a little fun,
I'm gonna put a little antenna into him.
There you go, now we've got
a little wireless antenna
to help us appreciate that this
is a wireless access point.
So he'll be set up as a RADIUS client,
and then this RADIUS
server will be over here.
So the supplicant, this
will be just some laptop,
or somebody who's trying to get on,
or a smartphone or something.
He sends his RADIUS request
to the RADIUS client,
who then forwards it to
the RADIUS server itself.
Now the important thing
about a RADIUS server
is that this RADIUS server's
gonna be using certificates,
or user names and
passwords, or RSA tokens,
or something that's coming
from the supplicant.
But the actual database
itself of user names
and passwords or any of that stuff
doesn't have to physically
be on this computer.
In a lot of situations,
this could be like a Windows
domain controller or something
like this, and the RADIUS
server can actually go ahead
and authenticate against
domain names in a domain
account or something like that.
So this is a pretty
standard setup for a RADIUS.
Now the thing you need
to remember about RADIUS
is RADIUS is gonna be running on UDP.
It's gonna be running on port
1812 or 1813 or 1645 or 1646.
Now here's the big thing you need
to keep in mind about all this.
The challenge we're running
into is that RADIUS is AAA.
So it's authentication,
authorization, and accounting.
So it authenticates people,
it authorizes and determines
what they can do, and it
keeps track of who does what.
There is another version of AAA that is on
the Network+ that you need to be aware of.
It's called TACACS+.
TACACS+ is actually a
proprietary Cisco product,
and it came to being
because Cisco had a lot
of customers who had routers and switches,
and people were going
nuts having to log in
to all of these different routers
and switches individually,
and they wanted to come
up with a AAA situation
that would allow people
to handle management
of a large number of routers and switches.
And that's where Cisco
came up with TACACS+.
Now I want to do this
again, except this time
let's put some TACACS+
stuff into the game.
Okay so first of all, TACACS+ is
rarely used in a wireless network.
I'm not saying it isn't used,
but it's not very common.
So I'm gonna start off
with the TACACS+ client.
Now what I'm talking
about here as a client,
is this is one of a bazillion different
routers that are in an enterprise.
It could be anything like that.
Now along with that is going
to be a TACACS+ server.
Now this is gonna be some
computer within the enterprise
itself that's keeping
track of all these things.
A TACACS+ user is really just
somebody who's logging into
the network and wants to
get to a bunch of routers.
So the whole idea of
supplicant doesn't really come
into play with TACACS+
like it does with RADIUS.
Not to worry, the one thing
you do need to remember,
and this is gonna be on the Network+,
and that is that TACACS+ uses TCP port 49.
So make sure you always
can appreciate that
TACACS+ uses TCP, and then
RADIUS is gonna use UDP.
So the whole reason we really
talk about RADIUS and TACACS+
at the same time is because the one thing
they do have in common
is they're both AAA.
They both authenticate, they
both authorize, and they both
account, keeping track of who's
doing what, when, and how.