- Authentication really
got started with PPP
and the many variations of PPP
that have evolved over the years.
However, PPP was really
kind of a reactionary type
of authentication designed
for dial-up type connections,
remote connections, and while
it worked fine it that way,
we really needed something
completely different
for wired local area networks
where I've got a bunch
of computers together
and they're all wired with Ethernet.
We have a lot of efficiencies in terms
of speed of network and things like that
that a better, I don't
necessarily wanna say better,
but a different form of authentication
can really take advantage of that.
And that's where Kerberos comes into play.
Kerberos is designed to do authentication
for local area networks.
Now, it can do more than that,
but that's its claim to fame.
Kerberos works completely
different from any
of the PPP concepts that
we've seen in other episodes,
so we really need to talk
about Kerberos in some detail.
So, let's go ahead and get started.
In order to appreciate how Kerberos works,
I'm gonna put two little blocks up here.
This is going to be a Windows Client,
so it's running Windows 7,
Windows 8, something like that.
But over here, this computer
is running a version
of Windows Server, so it's
running Server 2008, Server 2012.
This is not your regular Windows.
This copy of Windows right here is gonna
set you back a couple of grand probably,
and it could cost you a lot more.
But in return for that,
you have the ability
to turn this into what's known
as a Key Distribution Center.
When you set up a Windows Server
to be a domain controller,
it becomes a Kerberos
Key Distribution Center.
The Key Distribution Center consists
of two really, really important services.
First is the Authentication Service
and the second is the
Ticket-Granting Service.
So, that's all built into this guy.
So, what takes place is,
when your computer logs in,
he sends over a hash with his values
for username and password,
it's taken a look at
by the authentication server
and the authentication server then,
in turn, sends back a TGT token
to the client himself.
That gets him authenticated,
but he's not authorized.
The TGT is then timestamped by the client
and sent back over to the
Ticket-Granting Service.
The Ticket-Granting Service reads this,
stamps it again with a timestamp,
which, in essence, turns it
into something called a token,
and the token is then
passed back to the client.
This token is good for, well,
it depends on how you got it set up,
but eight hours is a fairly
common amount of time.
Any time your computer wants to log into
any other computer on the network,
as long as they're all
part of the same domain,
the same active directory,
he'll use that token
to access any resource
on any other computer.
Kerberos is some powerful stuff.
It's pretty much trivial to set
up, but it's wildly popular.
Anybody who uses Windows domains
and has domain controllers
is using Kerberos by default.
However, Kerberos has
a couple of downsides.
The first downside is that, well,
you gotta buy a copy of Windows Server.
It's fascinating, I go to
a number of universities
where they're doing big
parallel processing,
they've got gazillions of Linux boxes,
but they still buy a copy
of Windows Server just
so all their Linux boxes
can do a single log in.
It's very popular like that.
The other downside to Kerberos is
that everything is timestamped.
And especially during that transaction,
you have an extremely
short amount of time,
where it's preventing
man-in-the-middle attacks,
and if you don't get it in
the right amount of time,
it completely fails.
So, you have to have
all of your computer set
to the same time.
Now, that's relatively easy today,
with things like the
Network Time Protocols
and that type of thing, to set them up,
but a common problem, when
you have a Windows system
and you're trying to log into a domain
and you're unsuccessful,
one of the first things
you do is check the time.
Kerberos is great, but
Kerberos is really designed
for wired networks.
PPP is great, but the
challenge with PPP is
that it's really set up primarily
for point-to-point protocols.
So, what we end up having is
this fabulously complicated
world where we have all
of these different forms
of authentication mechanisms.
So, to try to fix this,
many, many years ago,
we came up with something called EAP.
EAP is nothing more than, well,
it's an envelope.
What EAP does is it
allows transactional-based
authentication mechanisms to be able
to talk to each other and go,
hey, I can do these
types of authentications,
what can you do?
And it allows a lot of flexibility
where before you would have to go,
well, we have to set it up so
it can only do certificates
or it can only do a password
or whatever it might be,
but with EAP, you now have
outrageous flexibility.
The best way to think about EAP is simply
to think about it as an envelope.
It's a burst of data that's
being sent between some type
of requester and some type of server,
and the EAP helps negotiate
to determine what you can do.
So, the trick here is,
when somebody's sending
to something else, they
have to ask each other,
well, what kind of EAPs can you do?
So, there's a number of EAPs,
let's go through the big ones at least.
EAP-PSK basically has a common key
that everybody uses to log in.
Another one is EAP,
which is known as PEAP.
With PEAP, it uses a standard
username and password.
There's very simple ones
that aren't used very often.
For example, there's one called EAP-MD5
and it simply uses a hash.
Now, if you wanna get hairy about things,
you can even use certificates.
For example, you can do EAP-TLS,
which is a single certificate,
which comes from the
server side of the system
and then passed to the individual clients.
You can even do EAP-TTLS,
which requires both the individual clients
as well as the authenticating system
to each have certificates.
EAP was designed as a methodology
of encapsulating any
form of authentication
that anybody could possibly wanna do.
The idea behind it is that with EAP,
we really wouldn't have
to worry about what type
of authentication methods you used,
we would just have the
ones that we're ready for,
and no matter what you
needed, we had it for you.
Well, it didn't really work out that way.
With EAP, even though
it works beautifully,
the only other real challenger
that's heavily used is Kerberos,
and Microsoft isn't gonna change that.
So, it boils down to
this, EAP is out there,
but it's pretty much
used almost exclusively
to connect to wireless networks.