- Well, what I wanna cover in this episode
is identification, authorization,
and authentication.
Now, when we talk about
these three, the best way
to really understand it
is through an analogy.
So, I'm actually buying myself
a ticket to go to the theater
right now, and I'm gonna print
out my confirmation code.
Let's go to the theater, and let me
show ya how these three work.
Two tickets for La traviata, please.
Now, before she's gonna
give me any tickets,
we are gonna have to get,
in essence, authenticated.
Now, the first step I'm
gonna have to do here
is I'm gonna have to provide
some form of identification.
In this case, I'm just gonna
provide a driver's license.
Now, because the ticket
lady's a human being,
this is an easy way
for her to identify me,
is just by looking at
the driver's license.
But, it still doesn't
mean I'm authenticated
to get some tickets.
In order for me to do, ah, yes,
in order for me to do that, I'm gonna have
to pull out my confirmation number
that I printed out on my printer earlier.
Now, between my identification
and my confirmation number,
I've actually performed
proper authentication.
Thank you very much.
And now, I've got my tickets.
Let's go sit down.
OK, row T,
and my seats are 14 and 15.
OK, looks good.
I think I might be here a little early.
The important thing to
remember for the Security+
is the difference between identification,
authentication, and authorization.
Identification just proves who I am
to the authenticating system.
Authentication itself
takes place by me proving
that I have rights to that
system through passwords,
smart cards, retinal scanners,
whatever it might be.
And then, authorization
simply means what rights
do I have to the system once
I've been authenticated.
Alright, so, let's do this all
over again, except this time,
let's do it in a more
computer kinda world.
I'm gonna watch the show.
Ah, La traviata.
Who doesn't enjoy a little bit
of Verdi every now and then.
OK, well, anyway, we're
back in the studio now,
and what I wanna do is kinda
make sure we understand
there are some issues when
it comes to identification,
authorization, and authentication.
The challenge we have is that,
well, computers aren't people.
I can't go up to a lady in a ticket booth
and just show 'em a driver's
license and confirmation
number and, in essence, get my tickets.
Instead, what we do is we have
what are called authentication factors.
Now, there are three big
authentication factors
that you're gonna be seeing on Security+.
The first one is something you know,
and that's something like a password,
for example, would be something you know.
The next one is something you have,
and that means things like a smart card
or something that you
actually have on your person
that you can use to authorize you.
And the last one is something about you,
and that's what we call biometrics.
That's gonna be things
like retinal scanners
and things that actually measure the veins
in your palm, all kinds
of cool stuff like that.
Anyway, let's go ahead and
start with the first one,
and that is something you know.
So, the best example
is good old passwords.
So, here we are at a
typical log in screen,
and you can see that I have my username
that I type in and my passwords,
we're all pretty comfortable
with something like that.
But passwords aren't the only
type of something you know.
Another great example
are gonna be PIN codes.
Now, we see PINs all over the place.
One of my favorite ones is
here on my phone right here.
So, what I'm gonna do is,
uh, you guys are gonna
fuzz all this out, right?
OK, so, what I'm gonna do
is punch in my password.
One, two, three four,
it's not a password, Mike,
it's a PIN, yeah, I know, it's OK.
Oo, it's incorrect.
Like I was really gonna let
you guys see my PIN code?
Come on.
Now, we see PINs all over the place.
We see 'em on phones a lot, ATM machines,
but, again, that's a great
example of something you know.
In fact, for certain
Department of Justice folks
I work with, not only, when
you walk up to a machine,
do you have to type in a password,
but you actually have to type in a PIN
separately, depending on what type of
authenticating system you might have.
But that's not the only
types of something you know.
There's two more I wanna look at.
First of all, let's
take a look at captcha.
We've probably all seen a captcha screen.
Most the time, these tend
to pop up on websites
where you're logging in
a few too many times,
and you're making the authenticating
process a little bit nervous.
So, what they're gonna do
is they're gonna let you
type in your username and password again,
but you're gonna have
to type in the captcha.
You know what that captcha says.
The idea here is that it's
preventing evil computer
programs that can just keep
logging in over and over
again from being able to log in.
So, that's captcha.
Now, the last one I wanna
take a look at is right here,
and this is going to
be security questions.
And there's a good chance most of us
have seen security questions too.
Security questions usually
pop up, for example,
when you've forgotten your
password or something like this,
and it allows for an automatic
password-retrieval-type system
simply by you remembering
the name of your first dog
or your mother's maiden
name, or your school
that you graduated from,
whatever it might be.
So, you need to be careful
on the Security+ exam right here.
It's easy to remember
that something you know
would be an example like
a password or a PIN.
But also remember that
captcha and security
questions are included
in something you know.
OK, the next one is something you have.
Now, when we talk about
something you have,
we're gonna talk about
two things in particular
that you're gonna see on Security+
The first one is called a smart card,
and I seem to be out of
smart cards right now,
but I got a picture of
one here on the screen.
Let's take a look at this.
Now, this is a very typical
smart card that you'll see used
in a lot of federal organizations
and stuff like that.
The important thing about a smart card
is embedded somewhere on that smart card
is a chip that holds a
unique identifying code.
And when you insert this,
or when you wave it over
a sensor or whatever it might be,
it provides that code to
the authenticating body.
Now, smart cards are
great, but the last one
I wanna show you is known as an RSA key.
Now, an RSA key, it can be a little device
that is got a number, or it
can be a piece of software.
And I actually have one here,
so let me show ya how an RSA key works.
Now, I want you to
watch this very closely.
You'll see this eight-digit code, watch.
OK, you see it just change?
An RSA token or an RSA
key is a piece of software
or an actual physical key you can get
that stores a secret code of some form.
It then takes that
secret code and performs
some magic little voodoo
on it and will generate
a value that changes, it depends,
there's no law of physics,
every 30 seconds, every 60 seconds.
So, the only way that another
device can authenticate
this is that if it also
has that secret code.
And it will go ahead and
run the same mumbo jumbo,
and if it comes up with the same value,
you are in good shape.
Now, the last one is something about you.
And when we talk about
something about you,
we're talking about something
about you physically.
So, we could have fingerprint
scanners or iris patterns
or even the pattern of
the veins in your wrist
can be used to identify you uniquely.
Now, there's a bunch of
these that are out there.
If you've got a late-generation iPhone 5,
there's fingerprint scanners
and things like that.
But what I have here is my
buddy Scott has a cool laptop,
and on this laptop is facial recognition.
So, to use this, all I'm gonna have to do,
and this allows him to
log into his laptop,
so, what I'm gonna do here is
I'm gonna fire the laptop up.
So, on his laptop, he's actually just
using the camera here to recognize me.
Now, if you look on the screen,
you see it's actually trying
to find Scott Jernigan,
so we might have a bit of a problem.
- [Scott] Hey, where's my laptop?
- [Mike] Oh, sorry Scott.
- [Scott] Mike.
- [Mike] I was just tryin' to show people
how Security+ covers things
like something you are.
- Pretty slick, huh, Mike?
- It is slick.
Thank you for letting
me steal your laptop.
- Thanks, uh, ya all done?
- We're done, we're done,
take it away, Jeeves.
(laptop closing)
- Bye.
- Bye, look forward to stealing
more from you in the future.
OK, so, that is a great
example of something about you.
Now, there are two more on the Security+
we need to talk about.
One of them is called something you do.
And when we talk about something you do,
there are actually authentication programs
where if you log in your
password, for example,
not only do you have to
have the right password,
but, literally, the rhythm of your typing
can be used to verify that it's actually
your kinda typing style,
which is pretty cool.
Now, the last one I wanna talk
about is called somewhere you are.
And when we talk about somewhere you are,
as it implies, it has
to do with geography.
So, the best way to show you this
is let's go buy some gasoline.
Now, somewhere you are has to do, well,
we see it in a lotta
places on authentication,
but one place we see it a lot
is in the credit card world.
(keypad beeping)
For example, here I am buying gas,
and it wants me to enter my zip code.
(pump beeping)
Hey, it works.
So, I'm gonna put regular in here.
Now,
the other thing to
remember about somewhere
you are is that this is also used
by credit card companies to detect fraud.
So, for example, while I'm
here in Houston, Texas,
if someone else were
trying to use this card
in Chattanooga, Tennessee,
that would definitely
set off some alarms at
the credit card company.
Those are the types of authentication
or, really, identifications,
that we run into.
So, the challenge that
we start to get is that
we do a lot of authenticating
all over the place,
and if I've got one network over here,
and then there's a company, and we access
their data a lot for
some reason or another,
the hassle of authenticating
from one place
and then another can
be a bit of a problem.
So, with a lot of operating systems,
in fact, well, let me rephrase that,
with Microsoft Windows in particular,
we can actually create
authentications based on trust.
So, here I've got three
different networks.
And, in this particular situation,
these are three different companies
that access this one company's database.
So, what becomes interesting
is that we can set up
what are known as a
federated trust situation.
And when we say federated
trust, it's basically
this system saying to
this system if you've got
somebody you trust, then
I'll trust 'em as well.
And what we can do, and
this sets up in Windows
fascinatingly under Active
Directory, is we can set
something up, and we can
actually establish a trust.
We can connect to another Windows domain
and say this domain trusts this domain,
and it can automatically
create these types
of federated, transitive trusts.
The last thing to throw
in here is the idea
of what we call
multifactor authentication.
You would never, ever use a biometric
as a primary and only
source of authentication.
Typically, what you're
gonna do is pretty much
everything works with a
username and password,
or it could be a PIN number.
So, if you're gonna
authenticate on a system,
you're going to use a fingerprint scanner,
and you're gonna type in
a username and password.
You're gonna type in a
username and password,
and you're gonna use a hardware token.
So, we're always doing the multifactor
form of authentication.