- I've got a laptop right here,
and it's got some resources on it
that I want people to have access to.
I might have some Word
documents in a folder,
some videos, whatever it might be.
And because he's on a network,
I want people from all over the network
to be able to get to my laptop.
Easy enough, but when
we start talking about
how we let people have access to stuff,
primarily within the networking world,
we run into authentication
and authorization.
Authentication basically
means what does it take
for you to get into the network,
the system, the computer,
the resource, whatever it might be?
And when we're talking about this,
we're talking about things
like user names and passwords.
We're talking about certificates.
We're talking about RSA tokens.
We're talking about smart
cards, retinal scanners,
whatever it might be, to allow the world
for it to know that you are
who you're supposed to be.
Now once we're in there, though,
so once we're authenticated,
now it's, well,
what can Mike do in there?
And that is where
authorization comes into play.
So make sure you understand the difference
between authentication
versus authorization.
Now the cornerstone to
pretty much everything
that takes place in this
process is something
that we know generically
as an access control list.
Access control lists exist everywhere.
On my computer I have
an access control list
that's pretty much user
names and passwords
and what people can do on folders.
On my wireless network I
have an access control list
that determines the password,
channels, things like that.
On my internet connectivity
I've got an access control list
that blocks port numbers
and things like that.
So access control, this
is a very generic term.
And we have to think very
generically about this.
So it could be all kinds
of different things,
but understand that there's
almost always going to be
some type of access control list
when it comes to authentication
and authorization.
Now in particular, authorization
is kind of interesting,
because over the years they've come up
with a number of ways to do this.
So what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna use folders
as my analogy here.
And there are three
types of access control
that you need to be aware
of for the Network+.
The first one is known as
mandatory access control.
In a mandatory access control world,
you would put labels, for
example, here's Top Secret,
on an actual resource itself
and, based on the label,
defined what you could
or could not do on that
particular resource.
So it was pretty much either
you could access the resource
or not access it.
So Top Secret, as you can tell, this came
from the US military,
so it's kind of an
old-fashioned way to do it.
Now there's nothing wrong
with mandatory access control
other than it was a little bit limiting.
So over the years, they
came up with another type
called discretionary access control.
With a discretionary access control,
you could actually define the resource
in lots of different ways.
For example, you can put the
term Owner onto a user account.
So Mike is the owner of this resource.
Other people can be
readers of the resource.
Other people can write to the resource,
whatever it might be.
But discretionary gives a
little bit more flexibility
with the old-school
mandatory access control.
Now this was good, but what
we really do tend to use today
more than anything else is
role-based access control.
So with a role-based access control,
we can finally use something
called groups, yay!
So with groups, what we could do is
we can then create users,
put the users into a group.
Now pay attention here.
And what we can do is we can
assign rights and permissions
to a group to define what it
can do with a shared resource.
So if you take a look at, for
example, Microsoft Windows
and what they call their best
practices, they have a mantra.
If you ever go for
Microsoft certification,
and we all have this memorized,
and it's that users go into groups
who then get rights and
permissions to folders.
So with role-based access control
we can use groups to provide
all kinds of flexibility
that we don't see with mandatory
or discretionary access controls.
So for the Network+ make
sure you can memorize
mandatory access control,
discretionary access control,
and role-based access control.