- One of the big challenges
to using asymmetric encryption
is the fact that well, if you're gonna do
asymmetric encryption, you're
gonna generate a public,
public keys will be red this
time, and a private key.
So you're gonna generate this key pair.
Now in this particular example,
let's say that I'm a web server
and I own a company called Total Seminars
and the website is www.totalsem.com
and I want people to be able
to buy stuff on my website.
So I wanna set up a secure web server.
So in the most simple
world, what I would do
is I would generate a
public and private key pair
and any time anybody
logged into my website,
I would automatically just
send them this public key
and then that way we could
start asymmetric encryption.
Well, that's a problem.
That's a big problem.
The problem with asymmetric
encryption is the public key.
If you get a public key from somebody
and by the way, when you
log into a secure website,
when you type in https://www.ebay.com,
you automatically get the public key
sent from that website
straight to your system, okay?
So it's not like email where we have
to send it via email
or anything like that.
But the problem is do you, as a person
who is running a little web client,
do you know that this public
key is for www.ebay.com?
Yeah, it may say it up on the screen
but there's ways to get around that.
So the problem with asymmetric encryption
is not the public private key,
that works pretty much perfectly.
The problem is in the key exchange.
How do you know A, where did
this public key come from
and B, is it the person
that you think it is?
So there's two problems here.
So in order to get around
this, there's actually
something really cool
I wanna tell you about.
Now remember we've said
in previous episodes
that you always encrypt
with the public key
and you decrypt with the private key
and that's true but I'm gonna let you know
on a little secret.
There is no difference between
a public and a private key.
I mean, they're different numbers,
they're just binary strings
and they're different binary strings
but there's nothing special
about the public key
that it can only encrypt.
There's nothing special
about the private key
that it can only decrypt.
When you generate a
public-private key pair,
either one of these
could be the public key.
Just by convention, we
pick a particular one.
So again, the public and private key
are just a string of ones and zeros,
they're different strings
but they're just strings
of ones and zeros.
Anything you encrypt with this
can be decrypted with this.
Now we never do that.
We never, never, ever do that.
The reason we don't do it is because
if we started to encrypt
with both sides of this,
there are ways that it can be hacked
and naughty things happen, we
don't want to ever do that.
However, there are some
cool things we can do.
Let me give you one example.
So again, I'm gonna go
back to www.totalsem.com.
I generate a public and private key,
you log into my website, got it?
Now what I'm gonna do
is I'm going to send you
the public key but I'm not gonna send you
the public key by itself.
What I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna take the webpage
that you're on right now,
whatever that webpage is,
and I'm going to encrypt
it with my private key
and then I'm gonna send you
a hash of that webpage, got the idea?
So when I send you my public key,
I'm not just sending you the public key,
I'm gonna literally
take the entire webpage,
encrypt it with my private key,
and then I'm gonna make a hash out of it
and I'm gonna send you,
not only my public key,
but a hash of the page
that you're on right now.
What you can do is 'cause you're getting
that webpage too is with your public key,
you can encrypt that entire webpage,
it's the exact same page, hash it
and compare the hash that I sent you
with the hash that you've generated
and you now know without
any question mark whatsoever
that whoever is associated
with this private key
has sent you the public key.
Do you understand the power of that?
It gives us a little
bit of a tool that says,
yep, whoever has this private key
has sent me this public key.
And we call that a digital signature.
A digital signature is just
a hash, that's all it is.
So if it's a webpage, we
encrypt and hash the webpage,
if I'm sending you a public
key for email encryption,
whatever email that I'm
sending you at that moment,
I'm gonna go ahead and
encrypt it and hash it
and whatever it is, we have now
generated a digital signature.
And a digital signature is nothing more
than a hash of whatever chunk of data
that you happen to be looking at,
encrypted chunk of data that says,
this had to have come
from this private key.
Well that's great but it's not complete,
see, the problem we run into now is again,
let's go back to my www.totalsem.com
and so you go on
www.totalsem.com and you go
and you wanna start buying stuff
and it kicks over into a secure webpage
so boom, comes down the public key,
boom, comes down my digital signature.
Did it really come from www.totalsem.com?
I mean sure, it says
www.totalsem.com but I can beat that.
There are ways that I can spoof
those addresses and fool you.
But what if I stole
somebody else's certificate?
What if I stole a certificate
from www.intel.com
and passed that down?
The problem you have now is
that you can't say for sure
that I, Mike Meyers, am the person nor I,
totalsem.com am the person from which
this public-private
key pair was generated.
So to get around that, what we're gonna do
is you and I are gonna shake hands
and before we start doing any business,
we're going to agree on a third party.
Let's say you and I both know
my buddy Janelle, alright?
So what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna go to Janelle
and I'm gonna say, hey
Janelle, I would like you,
because you and I know each other,
we've been friends for 30 years,
I want you, and by the way you
have one of my public keys,
I have your public key, whatever,
what I need you to do is generate
your own digital signature
not based on this relationship here
but based on your and my relationship.
And what I'd like to do is
attach that digital signature
to my public key along
with my digital signature.
So what we've done now
is we have a public key,
and this public key
says, well my public key.
Then we have a digital
signature which guarantees
that whoever actually
owns that private key
is associated to that public key,
and then we have a third party that says,
yep, I guarantee, well as much
as money and law will allow,
that this is Mike Meyers and
it's the www.totalsem website
and it is okay.
So this all sounds pretty good.
But we don't ever send
public keys by themselves.
We don't send piles of keys
with all these digital
signatures I guess with email,
we can make three
attachments or something,
what we do instead is
we generate something
called a digital certificate.
A digital certificate is a document,
it's like a Word document.
It's like a halfway
filled in Word document
and then you just fill in the blank spots.
And if you send anybody a public key,
you don't send a public key
by itself, it's never done.
You send a certificate and
inside that certificate
is going to be my public key,
it's going to have, let me
make sure I get the right one,
it's gonna have my digital signature,
knowing that it came from my key pair,
and it's going to have the third party
that you and I trust that says,
yep, this is really Mike Meyers.
What we normally do is
we go to a third party
and we go, would you
create me a certificate?
And that person knows us in some fashion,
maybe we have met with
them, they know my company,
whatever it is, and they will,
and they already have my
public key so if they don't,
I can hand it to 'em,
give 'em my public key,
give 'em my digital signature
and then they will generate a certificate.
The actual process of
generating a certificate
is trivially easy.
You can do it in any copy of Linux,
any copy of Microsoft Windows,
and you can generate this certificate.
They'll generate the certificate
but what they do that makes it important
and good and amazing is that they add
their third party digital
signature that says, I'm good.
And that's where the challenge comes in.
Oh and by the way, once
I have this certificate,
I can pass it out to anybody.
I can take this certificate,
put it into my web server
and anytime anybody
logs into my web server
and once it goes secure, boom,
they automatically get a copy.
I can, if I wanna do this for email,
I can take this certificate,
embed it into any email,
not an encrypted email,
just a regular email
and go hey, here's my certificate,
we pass out certificates like crazy
because this is how we move public keys.
Okay, the trick here is who do you trust?
Because the whole power of a certificate
is that we have people that we trust,
well that the two sides of
this equation trust and say,
yep, this is somebody I'm going
to trust and do business with.
So there's really three ways to do trust.
The first way to do trust
is to generate a certificate
on your own, forget the third party,
just make your own certificate.
It's easy enough to do.
And that's called an unsigned certificate.
Unsigned certificates are fantastic
as long as both people understand
that there is no third
party vouching for you.
We use unsigned certificates
here at Total Seminars.
I have some in-house web servers
and people wanna access
them, we all know each other,
I mean you can't even
get to this web server
unless you're an employee of mine.
So unsigned web servers,
they are very common
and they work fine but only if you have
some other form of trust
like you work for me.
Other than that, you've
got two other choices.
Web of trust and PKI.
So let's start with web of trust.
I've got a little graphic for you
to show you how that works.
So here's me and I want
to get a certificate.
Now in order for me to get a certificate,
in this particular
situation, this web of trust,
we don't have a particular authority
so what I have to do is find other people
who are using this type of certificate.
So here's a couple of people I know
and I can get them to sign my certificate.
Now depending on how this is done
and you see this with
email a lot of times,
you almost never see it
in some web browsers,
what will happen is that I will have
to probably call this person on the phone,
I might have to send them a photocopy
of my driver's license,
it really just depends
on how rigorous a
particular web of trust is.
And now this web of trust can grow
so let's make this a little bit bigger.
And over time, with the web of trust,
you end up having a
fairly complicated setup
where you have a lot of
people who trust each other.
Web of trust works
beautifully as a trust model
for certificates but it has some problems.
The big problem to web of trust
is that it requires a lot of
people doing a lot of work
to administer and make this happen.
There's very little to web of trust
that's in essence automated.
You've gotta work hard
to keep it up and going.
That's why web of trust
has never really taken off.
It's had its moments
for email certificates,
it's had its moments for believe it or not
even hard drives encryption
and stuff like that.
But if you really wanna do trust
with certificates the right way,
you do something called
public key infrastructure.
Public key infrastructure
is a hierarchal method
that starts off with root
servers up at the top,
intermediate servers
and goes down to users.
So there's always a boss at the top.
Let me show you how this works.
Public key infrastructure is based
on the idea of a hierarchy.
At the top of this hierarchy
are what we call the
certificate authorities.
A certificate authority is an organization
that pretty much just issues certificates.
These are usually big companies,
probably the most famous is Verisign
but Thawte would be another
name that comes to mind.
There's just a few hundred of these
and these organizations simply based
on the full faith and credit
of your and my trust in them,
generate certificates that
everybody knows and recognizes.
Now if we have a lot of people
who are going to these
certificate authorities,
the challenge that we run into
is that they can get kinda busy.
So normally what we'll do is between us,
the users of those certificates
and the certificate authorities,
are intermediate certificate authorities
who are only there to take the load off
of the certificate authority themselves.
So basically we have a nice
little hierarchy like this.
PKI is the way we do the internet.
If you're gonna be
dealing with certificates
on the internet, particularly
in a eCommerce way,
you're gonna be dealing with PKI
and anybody who's ever set up a website
that actually uses https realizes
that you gotta go to people
like Verisign and Thawte
and folks like that.