- I'll bet everybody
watching this video has
at one time or another
been browsing the web
and suddenly they see an error
that looks something like this.
What we're looking at
right here is an example
of where the certificate itself has failed
and the browser will not allow us
to create a secure HTTPS connection.
So what I wanna do in this
episode is cover the types
of situations in terms of
three very specific scenarios
that can come up that can
cause these types of errors.
Now what I'd like to do
instead of just going
on and on is I've got a
conversation I very recently had
with my buddy Bill Saichek
what we were talking about
Conversation on Cryptography series,
where we came up with
this exact same situation.
So let's go through three scenarios
where you might run into
these types of errors.
And let's start with
probably the most common one,
self signed certificates.
- [Bill] So let's take a look
at a self signed certificate
and what the browser
actually will show us.
So the first thing I'm
gonna do is to make sure
that, in fact, we do have
the certificate ready
to go and we wanna make sure
that the browser is all set for HTTPS.
- [Mike] Okay so you're just gonna show me
it's a self signed certificate.
- [Bill] That's all I'm showing you.
- [Mike] Okay, okay.
- [Bill] Okay so we start
out by first bringing
up the bindings and that we will show us
that HTTPS is, in fact, in place.
- [Mike] And that's that 443?
- [Bill] And that's that 443.
- [Mike] Okay.
- [Bill] So if I go to edit, I can see
that there's a certificate associated
with the web server and so
now if I view the certificate,
I see that yes, in fact,
it is a valid certificate,
but I still don't know
if it's self signed.
So let's take a look at
the certification path
and that will tell me
that there is no trusted root authority,
there is no intermediate authority,
there is just the certificate
so that's my proof
that this is a self signed certificate.
- [Mike] Cool, so what does it
look like in a browser then?
- [Bill] Okay so if I close all of that
and now I go and let's take a look
and open the website.
The first thing I do it click on it
and let's get rid of that, okay.
So the first thing I do is click on that
and what you see is
that there is a message
on the screen that says that
something has gone sideways.
Now this doesn't necessarily mean
that the server's down
or there's a huge error
or that the zombie apocalypse
is about the happen,
it is simply a little warning.
So what I'm gonna do now is see
what the warning is telling us
so that I can decide
what to do from there.
So if I click on this little details,
now it'll show me there
error gobbledy-gook.
Now don't worry about
the error gobbledy-gook
at all because you will see
in every browser there
will be an error message,
but the error message will look different.
But that's not what I
really want you to focus on.
I want you to take a
look at the very bottom
of the screen over here where
it says go on to the webpage,
which says if you know
the certificate is trusted
and you know, therefore, the
web server can be trusted,
go ahead, it's your server.
But what they're saying
is we're just telling you
that there's a warning going on.
So we go on to the web page
and there we go, now
we're on the web page.
So that's how a self signed certificate.
It doesn't stop you
from using your website,
it just is a way of giving
you a little added protection.
- Another very common situation
that creates certificate error is
when the certificate actually expires.
This can be very embarrassing.
Like, for example, here
at Total Seminars I forgot
to pay the bill once and forgot
to get a new certificate
and we got this error ourselves.
So it's not terribly uncommon.
Let's take a look at expired certificates.
One thing I wanna show you
before we go any further is
that how do you get to see a certificate
when you don't have access
to the actual web server.
In that previous one, we went straight
to the web server to see the certificate,
but you can always see a certificate.
So here it's just a particular
web browser I have open
and it's got a problem.
You could always look at any certificate
just by clicking right here.
Now this time I'm using Chrome
and everybody's going to
be a little bit different,
but the important thing
is if you wanna see,
you're on a browser and you
wanna see the certificate
that's causing you trouble,
there's always a place to click
in the browser to actually
look at the certificate.
You don't have to go to IIS every time.
- No and in fact, there's nothing secret
or secure about a certificate.
Remember, anything that is private
or personal isn't in the certificate.
The certificate is only
the public information.
- Sure, sure.
So in this particular case I'm gonna click
on this and I've got
a certificate problem,
but I can pull up the
certificate right here
and we can inspect it.
So that's gonna be important,
for not only this
example, but the next one
as well is where you actually have
to go in and look at the certificate.
- Remember, it's very important that
when there are messages, error messages,
warning messages, and
regardless of the browser,
you should always pay attention
and look that there is,
in fact, a certificate.
The certificate will tell you what's wrong
if you look at it and then you
can make the final decision
whether or not to actually
use the certificate
or you go to the website or not.
- So now my problem here
is that it's kinda hard
for me to set up a gazillion web servers
with very specific errors so
I'm gonna cheat a little bit
and instead of going to a web browser,
I'm actually gonna pull
up some local certificates
so you can see this particular example,
which is an expired certificate.
You would be doing the same thing,
though, by just clicking in the browser.
So what I'd like to do here is, hmm,
see if I can find this guy.
So here's the certificate right here.
Now if you take a look at this guy,
first of all there's some big warning
and every operating system when you look
at certificates they're gonna put
up all kinds of ones, it just happens
to be with Windows they
put a big yellow triangle
up there to let you
know there's a problem.
And in this particular case,
it's not telling me exactly
what the problem is,
but I can read and look
where the expiration date is,
right there.
September 12th of 2015.
Yeah this one's just a little bit expired.
Let's face it folks, there are situations
where a certifying body is going
to revoke a certificate,
they're gonna take it away.
In order for us to know
if a certificate is valid,
we take advantage
of two technologies called CRL and OCSP.
Let's take a look and
see how these guys work.
Alright so I've got good old Firefox here
and I'm gonna go into
some configurations here.
Now let's click on options and,
on this particular version of Firefox,
it's under privacy and security.
You gotta scroll way down here.
Here, Bill, have you ever seen this one?
Query OCSP responder servers
to confirm the current
validity of certificates.
- [Bill] You know, I've seen that,
but I've never really
dealt with it too much.
What should we do?
- [Mike] I leave it checked.
By default it's checked
and I've always discovered
that that's pretty much a better way
to handle this type of stuff
because I'm going to lose a little bit
of speed, not much, like you were saying
with Chrome, it's not a big hickey,
but I enjoy that extra little bit
of security and there's
been some situations
in the past where that probably
would have saved somebody's bacon
so just go ahead and leave it checked,
but if you need some extra speed
or you're not that worried about it,
turning that off can kick
things in a little bit.
So here's three great
examples of situations
where you might get an
invalid SSL certificate.
For the exam, remember the
most important thing of all:
if you take the time and
actually read the error
on the screen as it happens,
it's probably gonna save you a lot of time
and it's probably gonna tell you exactly
where the problem is.
How you fix it depends on the scenario.